Marite Sapiets papers, Inclusive: 1882-2009, undated, Bulk: 1975-1995, undated
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society
Marite Sapiets papers
Inclusive: 1882-2009, undated, Bulk: 1975-1995, undated
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society http://www.baylor.edu/kestoncenter/
27
Sapiets, Marite
5 document boxes
The Marite Sapiets Papers contain materials produced or collected by Marite Sapiets, the Keston College’s principal researcher on religion in the Baltic states.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Marite Sapiets was born in England on February 20, 1948, into a family that had emigrated from Latvia. Although her grandfathers were Latvian, her grandmothers were Russian. She spoke fluent English, Latvian, and Russian which she learned as an exchange student at Moscow University. Sapiets earned a master’s degree for her study of links between religious groups and the Russian intelligentsia.
Marite Sapiets’ mother was a nurse. Her father Janis, an ordained pastor in the Latvian Lutheran Church in Scotland as well as a minister in the Church of Scotland, introduced her to Keston. In the 1970s, Rev. Sapiets headed the British Broadcasting Corporation’s research and information at Bush House and edited religious programming to the Soviet Union. Michael Bourdeaux recognized him as one of the founding members of Keston, and the College often consulted him on Soviet religious affairs.
In 1975, Marite Sapiets joined the Keston staff as a research assistant for Michael Bourdeaux’s book Land of Crosses with a focus on the religious rights movement among Lithuanian Catholics. She became Keston’s principle researcher on religion in the Baltic republics. Her articles on Catholics, Lutherans, and Seventh Day Adventists in the Soviet Union appeared in Religion in Communist Lands, Keston News Service, Frontier, British and American journals, and the 1988 book World Christianity: Eastern Europe. Sapiets translated from Russian into English The Unknown HomelandDL samizdat detailing the life of an Orthodox priest in the Soviet UnionDLas well as sections of The Chronicle of Current Events, The Case of Leonid Plyushch, and From Under the Rubble. In 1990, the Keston Institute published her book True Witness: The Story of Seventh Day Adventists in the Soviet Union.
Sapiets was unable to make the move to Oxford with Keston College for health considerations and became a freelance writer, translator, and commentator on Soviet affairs. She passed away on July 5, 2012.
Scope and Content
The Marite Sapiets papers cover the period from 1882 to 2009 with the bulk from 1975 to 1995. They focus on issues of religion and persecution of believers in the former Soviet Union and the Baltic states.
Series II. Literary Works is the largest in the collection and includes materials written and collected by Marite Sapiets while making research notes, translating, and working on books and articles. Main topics include, but are not limited to, the history and persecution of True and Free Seventh Day Adventists in the Soviet Union and a biography of Lithuanian-born Polish and British artist Marian Bohusz-Szyszko. Also included is correspondence with his wife Dame Cicely Saunders, the founder of St. Christopher’s Hospice, in which Bohusz-Szyszko served as artist-in-residence and where he died in 1995.
The two remaining series are smaller. Series I. Photographs contains images of Marite Sapiets and her father Janis. Series II. Subject Files includes materials collected by Marite Sapiets and her associate Michelle Mapp.
Arrangement
The Keston Center received Marite Sapiets papers as parts of the Soviet Union Seventh Day Adventist subject files and the Xenia Dennen papers. Sapiets’ notes and book chapter draft manuscripts contained in the Adventist subject files were organized into a Literary Works series. Materials previously filed with the Xenia Dennen papers were reprocessed and reorganized into series according to topic.
The Marite Sapiets papers are organized in three series: I. Photographs, II. Literary Works, and III. Subject Files.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to the Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 27.
Related Resources
Related references
Bourdeaux, Michael. “Keston Staff Marite Sapiets.” Email, 2020.
Bourdeaux, Michael. One Word of Truth: The Cold War Memoir of Michael Bourdeaux and Keston College. London: Darton, Longman and Todd, Ltd, 2019.
Dennen, Xenia. “Keston Staff Marite Sapiets.” Email, 2020.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Bloom, Anthony, 1914-2003.; Bohusz-Szyszko, Marian, 1901-1995.; Mapp, Michelle.; Sapiets, Marite.; Saunders, Cicely M., Dame.
Subjects (Organizations)
Orthodox Eastern Church.; Russkai︠a︡ pravoslavnai︠a︡ t︠s︡erkov)' -- Clergy.; Russkai︠a︡ pravoslavnai︠a︡ t︠s︡erkov)' -- Great Britain.; Russkai︠a︡ pravoslavnai︠a︡ t︠s︡erkov)' -- Ireland.; Russkai︠a︡ pravoslavnai︠a︡ t︠s︡erkov)' zagranit︠s︡eiămp;&.; Russkai︠a︡ pravoslavnai︠a︡ t︠s︡erkov)'.
Places
Baltic States -- Church history.; Baltic States -- Religion.; Soviet Union -- Church history.
Subjects
Bishops -- Great Britain -- Biography.; Christians -- Soviet Union.; Communism and Christianity -- Soviet Union -- History.; Emigration and immigration -- Russia.; Human rights.; Orthodox Eastern Church -- Dioceses.; Orthodox Eastern Church members -- Europe, Western.; Persecution -- Soviet Union.; Russians -- Foreign countries.; Seventh-Day Adventists -- Soviet Union.
Genres
Biographies.; Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence.; Manuscripts.; Photographs.
- Photographs, 1976, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  The Photographs series consists of one folder containing copies of undated color images of Marite Sapiets and a 1976 black and white image of her father Janis Sapiets.
  The series is in good condition.
  - Photographs: Marite Sapiets and Her Father Janis Sapiets, 1976, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Literary Works, 1882-1996, undated; 2
  The largest series of the collection, Literary Works, includes correspondence, handwritten notes, draft manuscripts, research materials, and book reviews produced and collected by Marite Sapiets while working on her books, articles, and translations. Sapiets’ book on Adventists in the Soviet Union was published in 1990 as Keston book 32 under the title True Witness: The Story of Seventh Day Adventists in the Soviet Union.
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Correspondence (1 of 2), 1980-1983 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Correspondence (2 of 2), 1984-1988 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Western Adventist Press Clippings (1 of 8), 1882-1885 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Western Adventist Press Clippings and Notes (2 of 8), 1915-1920 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Western Adventist Press Clippings and Notes (3 of 8), 1930-1945 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Western Adventist Press Clippings and Notes (4 of 8), 1954-1959 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Western Adventist Press Clippings and Notes (5 of 8), 1963-1968 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Western Adventist Press Clippings and Notes (6 of 8), 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Western Adventist Press Clippings and Notes (7 of 8), 1981-1985 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Western Adventist Press Clippings (8 of 8), 1986-1990, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: General Conference Bulletin Clippings and Notes, 1901-1922 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Soviet Press Clippings and Notes (1 of 2), 1971-1983 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Soviet Press Clippings and Notes (2 of 2), 1984-1990, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Chronicle of Current Events Clippings and Notes, 1971-1978 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Assorted Collected Articles and Notes (1 of 9), 1930, 1976, 1978-1984 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Assorted Collected Articles and Notes (2 of 9), 1985 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Assorted Collected Articles and Notes (3 of 9), 1985-1987 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Assorted Collected Articles and Notes (4 of 9), 1988, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Assorted Collected Articles and Notes (5 of 9), 1979 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Assorted Collected Articles and Notes (6 of 9), 1925, 1949, 1953-1981 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Assorted Collected Articles and Notes (7 of 9), 1985-1987, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Assorted Collected Articles and Notes (8 of 9), undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Assorted Collected Articles and Notes (9 of 9), undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Persecution: Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Conscientious Objection: Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Harassment of Believers: Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Physical Assault: Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Psychiatric Abuse: Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Infiltration: Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Searches: Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Confiscation of Religious Property: Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Disruption of Meetings: Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Loss of Parental Rights: Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Discrimination in Education: Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Attacks in Media: Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Trials: Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Arrests and Imprisonments: Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Seventh Day Adventist Leaders: Clippings and Notes, 1988, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Registered and Unregistered Seventh Day Adventists: Clippings and Notes (1 of 2), 1980, 1982, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Registered and Unregistered Seventh Day Adventists: Clippings and Notes (2 of 2), 1980, 1982, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Lithuanian Seventh Day Adventist Arijs Tomsons: Clippings and Notes, 1987-1988 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Zaokskii Adventist Center, Tula Region: Clippings and Notes, 1987-1989 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Clippings and Notes: Adventist Periodical "Slovo Primireniia", 1989 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Clippings and Notes: Adventist Periodical "Slovo Primireniia", 1990 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Materials Received from Mikhail Murkin and Notes (1 of 2), 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Materials Received from Mikhail Murkin and Notes (2 of 2), 1985-1986 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Ivan Motria Testimony, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: List of Seventh Day Adventist Documents in the Keston Archive, 1974-1980 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Copies of Keston Documents (1 of 3), 1974-1978 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Copies of Keston Documents (2 of 3), 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Copies of Keston Documents (3 of 3), 1979-1981 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Copies of Keston Documents and Notes: Vladimir Shelkov, 1975, 1977, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Copies of Keston Documents and Notes: Rostislav Galetsky, 1977, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Copies of Keston Documents and Notes: Christian Committee for the Defence of Believers' Rights, 1979-1980, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Chapters: General: Notes, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Chapter 1 "Appeal to Madrid": Notes and Manuscripts, 1975-1982, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Chapter 2 "The Adventists come to Russia": Notes and Manuscripts, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Chapter 3 "The Adventists under the Soviets": Notes and Manuscripts, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Chapter 4 "Vladimir Shelkov - the man and his life": Notes and Manuscripts (1 of 2), undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Chapter 4 "Vladimir Shelkov - the man and his life": Notes and Manuscripts (2 of 2), undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Chapter 5 "The state atheist trial": Notes and Manuscripts, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Chapter 6 "Render to Cesar": Notes and Manuscripts, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Chapter 7 "The evidence of the witness: Part I": Notes and Manuscripts, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Book: Adventists in the Soviet Union: Chapter 7 "The evidence of the witness: Part II": Notes and Manuscripts, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Book: The Unknown Motherland: Mombrays, 1978: Reviews and Correspondence, 1979, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Book: Between Hell and Heaven: by Zori Balayan: Amaras, 1997: Translation: Manuscript, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Article: One Hundred Years of Atheism: Religion in Communist Lands, 2008, Vol.12 (3): Copy (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Manuscript: The True and Free Seventh Day Adventists of the Soviet Union: A microcosm of Soviet anti-religious policy in practice: Application to Leverhulme Trust, 1981 January 30 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Unpublished Manuscript: Marian Bohusz-Szyszko: A Biography: Correspondence and Notes, 1995-1996 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Unpublished Manuscript: Marian Bohusz-Szyszko: A Biography: Computer Disk, circa 1995 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Unpublished Manuscript: Marian Bohusz-Szyszko: A Biography: Chapter I: Draft Manuscript, circa 1995 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Unpublished Manuscript: Marian Bohusz-Szyszko: A Biography: Chapter II: Draft Manuscript, circa 1995 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Unpublished Manuscript: Marian Bohusz-Szyszko: A Biography: Chapter III: Draft Manuscript, circa 1995 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Unpublished Manuscript: Marian Bohusz-Szyszko: A Biography: Chapter IV: Draft Manuscript and Notes, circa 1995 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Unpublished Manuscript: Marian Bohusz-Szyszko: A Biography: Chapter V: Draft Manuscript and Notes, circa 1995 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Unpublished Manuscript: Marian Bohusz-Szyszko: A Biography: Chapter VI: Draft Manuscript and Notes, circa 1995 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Unpublished Manuscript: Marian Bohusz-Szyszko: A Biography: Chapter VII: Draft Manuscripts and Notes, circa 1995 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Subject Files, 1985-2009, undated; 3
  The Subject Files include newspaper clippings, manuscripts, photographs, print materials, and correspondence pertaining to the religious situation in the Baltic states and to Metropolitan Anthony Bloom and the Russian Orthodox Diocese of Sourozh in the United Kingdom. Marite Sapiets collected the Baltic states materials while she was monitoring religious rights issues in the Baltic countries of the former Soviet Union in the 1970s and1980s. Materials pertaining to Metropolitan Anthony and the Diocese of Sourozh were collected by Sapiets’ associate Michelle Mapp, who was a member of the Russian Orthodox Church in the United Kingdom and belonged to the Diocese of Sourozh during the time that Metropolitan Anthony was its leader.
  - Subject File: Baltic States: Clippings, 1985-1994, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Subject File: Metropolitan Anthony Bloom and Sourozh Diocese: Metropolitan Anthony: Texts of Sermons, 1967-2002 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Subject File: Metropolitan Anthony Bloom and Sourozh Diocese (UK): Metropolitan Anthony: Obituaries, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Subject File: Metropolitan Anthony Bloom and Sourozh Diocese (UK): Metropolitan Anthony: Pravoslavnyi zhurnal zarubezh’ia Put’, Extraordinary issue, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Subject File: Metropolitan Anthony Bloom and Sourozh Diocese (UK): Program of the Conference in memory of Metropolitan Anthony of Sourozh, 2009 November 14 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Subject File: Metropolitan Anthony Bloom and Sourozh Diocese (UK): Metropolitan Anthony: Copies of photographs, 2009, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Subject File: Metropolitan Anthony Bloom and Sourozh Diocese (UK): Sourozh Diocese: Color 6x4 photograph of a wooden Orthodox chapel (no linguistic content), 1997 June 3 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Subject File: Metropolitan Anthony Bloom and Sourozh Diocese (UK): Sourozh Diocese: Brochure "A Pilgrimage of the Sourozh Diocese to the Tombs of the New Martyrs and Confessors of Russia", 2000 August 11-21 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Subject File: Metropolitan Anthony Bloom and Sourozh Diocese (UK): Sourozh Diocese: General (1 of 3), 2000-2005 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Subject File: Metropolitan Anthony Bloom and Sourozh Diocese (UK): Sourozh Diocese: General (2 of 3), 2000-2006 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Subject File: Metropolitan Anthony Bloom and Sourozh Diocese (UK): Sourozh Diocese: General (3 of 3), undated (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Subject File: Metropolitan Anthony Bloom and Sourozh Diocese (UK): Sourozh Diocese: Bishop Illarion, 2002-2006 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Subject File: Metropolitan Anthony Bloom and Sourozh Diocese (UK): Sourozh Diocese: Fr. Andrei Teterin, ally of Bishop Illarion v. Bishop Basil, 2005-2006 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Subject File: Metropolitan Anthony Bloom and Sourozh Diocese (UK): Sourozh Diocese: Court Case, 2009 April (Box 5, Folder 20)